Did you know that in the original Columbia Pictures logo
it was Irene Dunne that is photographed
standing there holding the torch ?
Of course , Columbia Pictures at that time had been bought by Sony .
And we begin the prologue of Dracula
which is intended to provide some historical background of the setting
the unique setting of the story of Vlad Tepes
who was the historical figure of Dracula .
The year , 1462 .
Constantinople had fallen .
Moslem Turks swept into Europe with a vast superior force
Striking at Romania , threatening all of Christendom .
From Transylvania arose a Romanian knight
of the Sacred Order of the Dragon
known as Dracula .
We begin the story with the tale of how the Sultan Mehmed II
finally was able to conquer Constantinople .
And it became the seat of the sultanate .
And of course , all the countries in that area
Romania being one
the Balkans were profoundly affected
by the presence of the Islamic sultan
that they 're so close in Constantinople
which had been the Byzantine empire .
And as Christians , the Romanians were caught between
the polarity of this very powerful Ottoman Empire
and the Christian European states , which were quite far away .
So in a sense , the Romanians were left to deal with this problem
and Vlad was a ferocious warrior .
And it was his reputation as the Impaler
that provided psychological warfare
for the superior Turkish Ottoman forces .
This prologue was pretty much created after the fact
by my son Roman , who was the second unit director
and did the special effects .
And of course , the problem was , we had very little money left
and decided to tell this opening prologue almost as a puppet show
with shadows and banners .
We didn 't have many people or soldiers
and told it in a very abbreviated form
which was storyboarded
and which used the great work of our colleague , Gary Gutierrez
who had worked on any number of title and special sequences
and helped us figure out how to tell all of this history
in a way that we could afford .
I mean , using images , in this case , dolls and puppets
and old-fashioned effects concepts
such as glass shots and hanging miniatures .
So when the young actress
Winona Ryder came to see me
and the purpose of our discussion was really
about the fact of how she had dropped out
of working on Godfather III .
Winona was supposed to play the young daughter
of the Godfather II story .
And when she came , she didn 't feel well .
And she basically withdrew from the film
leaving me in a tough spot for Godfather Ill .
Much later we talked about it
and I didn 't want to have a grudge against a young person
So I tried to be nice to her and say :
" Yes , I understand what happened . "
And she said , " Well , good , because I have this script of Dracula .
Would you consider doing it ? "
And , of course , that was a magic word to me
because I not only knew the book so well
from this experience reading it to my little boys
but also I knew about the historical figure of Dracula
who was Dracula , meaning the son of Dracul .
And Dracul was the Order of the Dragon
which was given to certain Romanian noblemen
because of their service in the very difficult situation Romania was in
being between the great Ottoman Empire , which was so close to it
and yet being Christian , and being , really , knights to defend Christianity .
And so this historical person , Dracula , who was really known as Vlad Tepes - -
So I knew a little bit about this historical king of Romania
and I knew the story of how Bram Stoker
had appropriated this history to combine it into a vampire tale .
So I agreed to do it .
It was a time when I was really sort of putting my life together
after some of the big financial setbacks that I had had
and which was what led me to make the third Godfather
and the Dracula picture , and kind of stabilize my life
at a time when it had been pretty rocky .
The costume designer
Eiko Ishioka , was given the challenge to try to find a new kind of imagery .
As example , his unusual armor .
This title was done , as was much of this whole prologue
by Roman and by our colleague Gary Gutierrez
a San Francisco filmmaker
who worked on many , many Zoetrope films
and was an Academy Award winner
for Phil Kaufman 's film The Right Stuff .
I 've done everything that you asked , master .
Tom Waits played Renfield , who was , like , the former real-estate man
who had gone off to Transylvania to attempt
to do a real-estate deal with this mysterious Count Dracula
as it 's told in the Bram Stoker book .
The Bram Stoker novel is written in an unusual way .
It 's written as a series of entries , notes , diary entries
or other documents , all in a pastiche
to move the story forward
which is basically the story of a young solicitor
or I think he was , like , a real-estate agent , as played by Keanu Reeves
Jonathan Harker , who is given the job by his firm
to go to the distant East European country of Romania
to that region of it which is called Transylvania
which technically was under the influence of the Hungarian empire
to conclude a business deal with Count Dracula .
He wished to buy some real estate in England .
what in fact happened to Mr. Renfield in Transylvania ?
Nothing . Nothing . Personal problems .
Close these transactions , and your future with this firm is assured .
Yes , Sir ...
So Harker is sent on his way
to make this trip by train to conclude it .
Of course , before going , he bids adieu to his sweetheart , his fiancé
as played by Winona Ryder .
Of course , they 're about to be married
and she 's very reluctant that he go away from her .
All of these settings
were done at the sound stages , formerly MGM , in fact .
This was a great big sound stage that had a pool .
And this was the pool where Esther Williams made all of her films
in the MGM era .
We begin now something that is part of the style of the picture
in that we pre-visualized , or pre-designed
how everything would work .
And my son Roman worked extensively on this
and shot many of these sequences .
These scenes you are seeing , with the train going over the diary
and the eyes and face of Dracula in the windows
were all done in-camera
meaning that the shot of him by the window was shot
and then the film was wound by hand .
In this case , the image of the map is projected on his face .
Everything is live . It 's not done in post-production
as it would be done in the modern times .
This plate that you see in the window
with the landscape of the Carpathian Mountains
and the eyes of the mysterious count
are all being combined in the film .
It 's an effect not unlike the great German silent director G. W. Pabst
or Murnau , who made Nosferatu , would have done .
Your friend , D.
It 's interesting , I see the letter , and he says , " Your friend , D. "
For a while , I was suggesting that we perhaps
just call the movie D. with a period
just to try to designate it as being a little different
from the more familiar Dracula movies .
But I guess that wasn 't such a good idea .
At any rate , it wasn 't an idea that was used .
It must be so nice to see strange countries .
I wonder if we , I mean Jonathan and I ...
The script , written by Jim Hart , tried to follow - -
And I agreed very much to follow the story
as it was in the book .
To make a version of Dracula that was very much like the book .
Not only did I know the book well - -
I used to read it to my little camp students when I was a camp counselor .
- - But also , I had the entire cast sit around for probably three days
and read the book aloud
something that really frustrated Anthony Hopkins .
Didn 't see for the life of him
why I wanted to have them read the entire book .
And of course , I did
because I wanted to be sure they all read the book .
And also , I was hoping we 'd discover something in the book
that had been left out .
We did work with wolves .
They were real wolves , and they 're tricky to work with .
You have to be very respectful of their territory .
The scene where the ghostly driver of the coach picks up Harker
was a problem for me at first
because I remember the book described
how the coachman just reached his hand over to Harker
and the hand just seemed to extend so far
and literally pick him up and lift him up into the coach .
And there was a lot of concern of how we could do this as a live-action
meaning this really was photographed as it was happening .
And the special-effect man went home
when we failed to know how to do it
and came back with a solution that was quite interesting
involving the coachman and Harker standing on boards of wood
that were leveraged in such a way that we could actually
move the coachman to reach for him , and move them into the room .
This shot is a glass shot
which means part of the scene is painted on a piece of glass
and then the real coach , which is in a sound stage
Is shot through that glass , or in conjunction with that glass
10 enable it to look as though you 're seeing the whole image .
This was a very common way to do effects
In the golden age of movies
before these things could be accomplished
with digital and other effects .
Much of this movie really is a theatrical illusion .
Which was my goal . I wanted to find a new way
to find imagery for the story .
... to find imagery for the story .
And I had this fabulous studio to work with .
Already , you can see one of the themes of the visualization
of the movie , which is the use of shadows .
It was my idea that in the presence of a metaphysical phenomenon
such as a vampire , that the laws of nature , of physics
don 't really work correctly .
Shadows seem to be liberated from the person casting them .
Things fall up instead of fall down .
That you know you 're in a realm of supernatural , because subtly
things don 't happen correctly .
Now , it 's well-known that once you step into the world of a vampire
you cannot be harmed unless you voluntarily take that step yourself .
And so when Harker takes those first steps over , across the threshold
he has willingly put himself into the realm of that vampire
and thus is in danger .
I was also told that once by Mario Puzo , in regard to the Mafia .
That the Mafia would be - - People who were truly in the Mafia - -
He had never met anyone that was actually associated in the Mafia .
And he advised me never to willingly know them
to let them know your phone number
or that you would be friendly with them .
And I often thought that the same rule was the rule of the vampire
that when dealing with the Mafia
if you did not invite them into your life
by way of accepting their friendship , or a gift - -
Which was probably stolen , by the way .
- - Or go to one of their good restaurants
that they could never have any - -
They would respectfully not intrude in your life .
And I always followed that rule given by Mario
and therefore , I never had any encounter
or any knowledge of any Mafia person
despite having made a film that was well-known about that group of people .
And by the same token
had Jonathan Harker not voluntarily walked over
Dracula 's threshold
he would not have been in danger .
Blood ...
Of course , this performance of Gary Oldman
attempted to blaze a new trail
making use of the historical Vlad Tepes
the picture of which is on the portrait .
And as well as a character
the eccentric count living in an old castle
that had been made so famous by Bela Lugosi .
And we felt very much that we were gonna go in another direction
for better or for worse , and try to find a new kind of imagery .
And part of this was , we were going to have costumes
and imagery that was totally different .
Forgive me .
Another interesting example
of the detail that my son Roman did .
In this scene , you begin to sense something strange
which is that the shadow is not moving exactly in sync
with the person casting it .
That 's because , of course , we were casting that shadow
with another actor who was done up in that costume .
And that enabled , again , these strange things of where
Dracula walks off to the left , and the shadow 's still there .
And yet he 's able to walk in from the right .
Clearly , Jonathan Harker should have noticed
if not alone from the hairdo and the strange red robe
that there was something amiss with this guy .
And that there was something very , very mysterious
in terms of the world he was entering .
Mr. Renfield .
Of course
there was the photograph of Tom Waits as Renfield
as had been the predecessor of Keanu Reeves ' character .
He was the one who went first , that they never heard from again .
Again , the shadow - - Whenever you see the shadow
and Dracula in the similar frame , you realize that they - -
The shadow seems to have its own will and its own movement .
And it was actually pretty tough to do .
The guy was there behind the scene , often , with a television monitor .
He was reputed to be an expert mime who could do this .
But it was much harder .
It was easy to do something so different
from what the principal was doing .
But what was harder was to have it match it , in a way
long enough to be a convincing shadow
before it had its own independent movement .
We 're to be married as soon as I return .
Are you married , count ?
Again , you see the shadow is independently moving .
I was married once .
Ages ago , it seems .
She died .
- Oh . I 'm very sorry . - She was fortunate .
My life , at its best , is misery .
Of course
the hair design was part of the costume , really
and part of the vision of Eiko Ishioka , who was the costume designer .
But she was really - - I hired her to do the costumes
but Eiko was a great graphic artist in Japan .
And I was looking for a really innovative design concept
for the way the characters would look .
Again , to get away from the Bela Lugosi , or the previous Draculas
which sort of all followed that direction
and tried to do something just more striking
and , you know , one of a kind .
And , you know , when you do things like that
you 're always on the verge of the ridiculous .
Again , that was an homage to John Carradine
the way he lifts up the cloak .
I always remember John Carradine in Dracula movies
doing that and turning into a bat .
The film , as I watch it now - - I haven 't seen it since , really , those days .
And it is and it was meant to be full of visual imagery
that tried to court the surreal and ...
In a great tradition of surrealism , of course .
The films of Jean Cocteau , and other films .
That 's my missing Persian print .
I can 't find that print . And I know I loaned it to the movies
to be able to do this scene .
And of my entire Richard Burton collection of Arabian Nights
that book is missing .
Is your ambitious John Harker
forcing you to learn that ridiculous machine ?
When he could be ...
There was some difference of opinion
on how I imagined the settings and the sets
vis-a-vis the costumes .
I had planned this notion that , in a sense
the costumes would be the sets .
And I didn 't want to have very , very distinctive and unusual
and elaborate sets .
And I did have a disagreement with the first production designer
who I felt went way over the top in terms of the , you know - -
It 's hard to tell a production designer that :
" Oh , well , in this movie , the costumes are the sets . "
And so ultimately , I was forced to fire him
something that shocked him greatly .
And I hired two young production designers
Tom Sanders and a wonderful young man named Andrew Precht
who rose to the occasion .
And in the difficulty of coming in
after the previous art director had left
leaving me there , Andrew and Thomas came in
and did a remarkable job .
my rich friend .
Yes , but not even one marriage proposal .
And here I am , almost 20 .
Practically a hag .
Mr. Quincey P. Morris .
- Oh , look . - What is that ?
The characters in Dracula , in this production of Dracula
the young doctor who is caring for Lucy
and the cowboy who comes in
are all quite authentically taken from the book .
And those characters all exist . There are many of them , her suitors .
Ultimately , they later on form the group
that follows the mad Dr. Helsing
who has his vampire Killers
many of whom were Lucy 's former suitors .
We had a wonderful group of actors who participated with this
and we got to rehearse together .
And , again , the costumes were so appropriate .
- - of love - - - Oh , Jack , my darling .
Onh , poor little baby .
My kitten , come over here .
Richard E. Grant , the wonderful British actor
whom I had seen in a movie called Withnail I
played Dr. Seward .
And Bill Campbell played the American .
This is the noble young lord played by Cary Elwes .
And they were such an enthusiastic young group of people .
They all came to Napa , I remember , for a week or so of rehearsal .
And I staged all sorts of wacky adventures
for them to go on , in order to bond together in character .
I remember that the three suitors , I ordered a hot air balloon to come
So that they could go ballooning together .
And one morning they came , and there was the hot balloon there
but it was too windy .
So they just went up , and it was tethered by a rope .
But they sort of had their adventure .
Again , we used the shadow of Dracula to begin to express his power
that from , literally , a coffin in the hold of a boat , or wherever he is
he is able to reach out to find her and threaten her , ultimately .
... he is able to reach out to find her and threaten her , ultimately .
But we also understand that she is the living likeness
almost the reincarnation of his long-lost love .
returns from business abroad in Transylvania ...
Partly , the movie was interested in technology
So there 's constantly new dictating machines
and new cinemagraphic devices .
George .
Here 's Eiko 's very curious costumes
for the people who work in the mental asylum .
It looks like they have cage boxes on their heads .
Presumably so the inmates can 't attack them .
Here we have the wonderful , brilliant Tom Waits
in a memorable performance .
I 'm heartbroken that when they showed this movie on television
they always cut these sequences out .
Perhaps they 're too weird . I know they 're trying to save time .
But it 's such a strange character .
And look at these odd things on his hands
10 prevent him from doing damage to himself .
And he , of course , is so thrilled to have his little creatures
because he , having been inoculated by Dracula
craves life , craves blood .
And makes do with the few insects he 's able to attract .
Of course , he is under the care of Richard E. Grant 's character
Dr. Seward .
And his behavior is notably being studied
as for what evidence it can ultimately then contribute
to the strange things that begin to happen in London
with the shadow of the oncoming of Count Dracula .
A Kitten .
I beg you .
A little , sleek - - A playful kitten .
Something I can teach . Something I can feed .
But the story originally , in the Bram Stoker novel
Is told in any number of excerpts , as I said .
The diaries of Mina Harker
or in this case , the medical journals of Dr. Seward .
- I need lives for the master . - What master ?
The master will come
and he has promised to make me immortal .
How ?
Get him off me !
The blood is the life !
Again , we have now a sequence executed by Roman
with multiple image .
Again , all done in the camera .
It was our idea that the castle of Dracula - -
Again to try to find imagery that could be a little different
than what was previously done .
But the castle itself of Count Dracula
looked a little bit like Dracula .
This was a live-action effect . Here you see there 's a mirror
and you don 't see Dracula reflected in the mirror
but you do see his hand .
And that was hard to do , and I don 't remember how we did it .
And then when he turns , of course , Dracula 's in another place .
And Dracula just seems to float around . Every little detail in the film
of how he moved or walked or what happened
was done in a stylized way to try to , again , express this idea
that in the presence of a metaphysical being
the laws of nature were all awry .
A foul bauble of man 's vanity .
Perhaps you should
grow a beard .
This , of course , was a memorable moment .
The way Gary did it , primarily - -
I 'm not exactly sure where the idea came from .
It may have been partly in collaboration with Gary Oldman
who is a very intelligent , inventive person
and , of course , who has directed films himself .
Good .
The photographer of the film was Michael Ballhaus
and he was a fine gentleman .
I think during much of the filming , he was very , um
confused as to what the overall concept of this film was .
I mean , it 's a journey into surrealism
and manipulation of imagery .
I mean , in this scene , things are happening - -
Perhaps you can 't tell , but the walls are actually moving in
closer and closer on them
producing the effect of being sort of closed in by the character .
But we were constantly moving walls
and having shadows that didn 't belong
or doing scenes backwards .
Our ways are not your ways .
There 's a real - -
Just a collection of old-fashioned visual effects
used in the picture .
And many times , you don 't really even see what 's happening
but rather , you 're feeling that you 're in
an extremely surreal environment
and that you 're in a world
not governed by any natural laws .
But most of it is in - - I mean , almost all of it
Is from the Bram Stoker book and from his imagination and lines .
I mean , there , the robe goes out , and the shadow goes after it to follow it .
I haven 't seen this for a while , but it 's full of - -
A treasure box of strange effects .
In this case , again , Bram Stoker described how Dracula
was seen to be able to crawl up the sides of buildings .
And , of course , we did many of these things
by having the set be lying flat on the ground
and having him crawl across the floor , basically
but looking as though he 's going up or down a building .
/ said nothing of my fears as he will read them , no doubt .
I know now that I am a prisoner .
Again , the laws of gravity being defied .
This is a multiple-image shot by Roman
which he did it in subsequent exposure .
You know , I - - You know , there are certain people
who basically don 't like this kind of theatricalization .
Although , you know , I mean , I think with Dracula
a movie that had been made SO many times
you either go one extreme , kind of - - Which I did .
A kind of theatricalized , do it all in the studio .
Or perhaps you could go in the opposite direction
and do an almost
super-real , naturalistic version of it .
I could see that . I mean , in that case , I would 've gone to Romania
and I would 've tried to endow the film with a kind of naturalism
despite the very
fanciful and surreal nature of the story .
But I knew that I had to go one way to the left or the right
of what the bellwether Dracula was , which was the Bela Lugosi Dracula .
Here , again , the drops float upward .
I was always trying to show that all of our familiar rules of existence
were being contradicted or defied .
So , you know , I think the photographer
was always resisting some of these strange notions .
Come .
Lay down .
Lay back into my arms .
We consulted with a magician
who builds equipment for stage magicians .
And we devised a special bed
out of which these brides could appear
and these footsteps could appear out of nothing .
But the idea was that these women should materialize right out of the bed .
And this young lady is , of course
the very well-known actress Monica Bellucci .
This was her first film .
She 's quite a beautiful woman .
I think Roman had seen her picture IN a magazine .
Whenever you have to shoot something involving sex , it is so tough .
You know , you are very clear when you cast the - -
In the case of women , because men are even tougher than women .
Men are so funny about showing as much as their bellybutton
God forbid anything else .
Of course , everyone is shy .
And even though , in this case , the girls had all agreed
that there would be nudity in their contracts
when they came onstage , they were all sort of covered up .
Then I would say , " Hey , Roman , tell them to take off their clothes . "
Roman said , " I won 't tell them to take off their clothes . "
He said to the assistant director :
" Oh , okay , tell them to take off their clothes . "
And nobody wanted to tell them to take off their clothes .
And that 's usually what it 's like .
But I agree that those scenes are not comfortable for anyone .
And when I see the Dracula material of that smoochy scene there
with them all kissing him and stuff , I was just dying .
And I just was so uncomfortable .
But I must say , in looking back at it , it really was okay .
The other brides - - There was a lovely young lady from Israel
as I remember . Her name was Michaela .
And the Romanian young lady was Florina .
And she also consulted with us on Romanian matters
and helped us speak the language .
She was quite a bright young lady .
Dracula 's entrance was on some sort of rail device
So we can just speed him right on the scene .
And then there was the strange motion of the two brides together
which was - - We had worked hard with Michael Smuin , a choreographer
to try to get the girls - -
And I think at one point , we had gymnasts involved in doing that .
But this was all in the desire to be constantly offering up
you know , kind of an experience that would
put you in the strange mood of the story .
I found it so difficult to do this scene
which so revolts Keanu .
But this was a brand-new little infant .
And I always thought , when I held this baby - -
It was only born recently from when we shot this .
I was so careful to do it in a way that exposed the baby
to the little bit of handling as possible .
But I always thought I would love to see that baby again .
I held her in my hands , and thought that .
That , " Oh , I 'd love to see you in future years . "
And it reminds me , I should try to find out who that baby was
So I can go bring her a present or something .
Dearest Mina , all is well here .
The count has insisted I remain for a month
to tutor him in English custom .
I can say no more , except I love you .
Ever faithful , Jonathan .
The letters I have written have undoubtedly sealed my doom .
The count 's gypsies , fearless warriors who are loyal to the death
to whatever nobleman they serve
day and night they toil , filling boxes with decrepit earth
from the bowels of the castle .
They are to be delivered
to his newly acquired Carfax Abbey in London .
Why do they fill these boxes with earth ?
In the shot of Dracula kind of rising up through the frame
that was what we call in the movie racket - - We call it an homage .
But that was for sure an homage for Nosferatu
in this extraordinary moment when the Dracula figure rises up in that way .
And I just had to have that in the movie
because it was something I always loved when I saw Nosferatu
which , as I 've said
Is probably the greatest Dracula movie ever made .
And a silent movie .
Mina , what is it ? It 's the most exciting day of my life
You don 't seem to care .
It 's just that I 'm so terribly worried about Jonathan .
This letter I received is so - -
This is the work of Andrew and Tom .
The garden , again , is built into the swimming pool
that was Esther Williams ' swimming pool .
You know , we wanted to show the effect of the coming of Dracula
even on the girl .
He 's on the ship , in his coffin , buried in the earth of Transylvania .
And it 's beginning to influence even those girls in England .
This is a sequence trying to express
the crates of boxes of Dracula 's belongings , including himself
in a kind of almost embryonic state in the box .
And , of course , the movement of the ship on the water
Is now translated even to the girls in their garden and maze
trying to unify the turmoil of storm
that is about to reach them .
As though the earth of this English estate is moving .
And the animals in the zoo are all becoming like a boat .
I would - - If I 'm trying to think back as to who this would be an homage to
would say Abel Gance
who was very , very comfortable with using the movement of the camera
to express a unifying idea such as this .
Crew uneasy .
Believe someone or something
Is aboard the ship with us .
You know , all hell is breaking loose in the asylum
because the coming of the boat - - Again , the metaphor is that
the boat is expressed by boat-like movement
even in a rock-solid place like an asylum .
But he 's getting so stoked , Renfield , that his master is coming .
And , again , authentically told from the book
Seward is shooting up himself with morphine .
And the emotion of all the characters is being intensified
by the mere approach of this prince of darkness
who arrives on the shore in England
and no doubt has killed and taken the blood out of all the sailors
So that it 's totally a dead ship .
And now using a technique called pixilation
in which we just shot a few frames at a time
to try to give a curious point-of-view look
for the spirit of Dracula .
Roman shot that pixilation .
I think it was a term
that comes from certain experimental filmmakers
maybe in the San Francisco period in the ' 50s .
It 's interesting that , you know , a filmmaker , you know
as a young person , I saw all this stuff , saw all these films
experimental films from San Francisco .
Jordan Belson , Stan Brakhage
the great works of G. W. Pabst and Murnau
and the other Dracula stories .
Carl Dreyer .
And all of us are really sort of , like , just receiving this
and then it 's all mixed up in our own personalities and souls .
And then we put it out in some new form .
It 's a process of gathering from everyone
and our own life experience
and then , like , putting it together
in a form that it had never existed before .
And , you know , I always tell the young filmmakers I meet
that , you know , the different writers , Balzac , and the different filmmakers
they want you to take what they 've done
and if they want , just copy it . Because you never really copy it .
It 's impossible for you to copy it .
You put it out in your own form , and then that makes the - -
I read that once , of Balzac , saying :
" Oh , we want the young writers to take from us
because if they take from us and put it in their work
then we 'll be immortal . "
And that is the tradition .
You 're inspired by others , and then , hopefully , if we 're fortunate
we inspire people who come after them .
I 'm a little surprised by this movie , is - -
I haven 't seen it in such a long time , but it never stops doing stuff .
It 's hard for me to talk about I , because normally
on doing a commentary on a movie - -
Oh , yeah , he 's , like , actually seeing the blood coursing through her veins .
These are all ideas that we hoped to do when we planned it out .
And then , of course , we had to find ways to be able to do this imagery .
But - - And some worked really very , very successfully , and some not at all .
But you can see that it was a production that was full of ideas
and basically innovations
to try to bring this old tale
this beloved , you know , horror classic
Stoker 's Dracula - -
Once again , to film without just following the path
of what had been done before .
You know , if it had used what had been done before , I would say :
" Well , yes , it used , you know , Beauty and the Beast by Cocteau . "
Or all these other references
that I 'm trying to acknowledge here and now
So that you can have the extreme pleasure of going back
to films like Beauty and the Beast and Nosferatu
and Vampyr by Carl Dreyer
and the other projects that have their DNA in this movie
as it were .
Swing it round here .
Master .
I am here to do your bidding .
Master ! I am here !
I have worshiped you .
Contrary to some beliefs , the vampire
like any other night creature , can move about by day
though it is not his natural time , and his powers are weak .
That was a good shot , is that - -
Like , he 's in this box , and he bursts out
young and healthy and so vital .
This sequence is actually shot
with a Pathé camera , hand-cranked camera .
I wanted to shoot much more of it with the camera
but the photographer was less than interested
but it really has a wonderful sense of the period .
This is really being shot
the way early silent movies were shot , on the same camera .
With uncoated lenses . Very , very intriguing .
I know there was lots of debate as to whether or not a vampire
could , in fact , walk around in the daytime .
Because in this scene , and in the book , there was a sense that it did happen .
And I was able to uncover , in the lore , as to where these things came from
such as a vampire can 't be seen in a mirror
and a vampire cannot walk around in the daylight .
But I - - And in this case , you see that he 's there looking at the window
but his reflection is not in the glass .
And I don 't remember it now , but I felt convinced that I had justification .
Whether it was in the Bram Stoker book or something else
that I could portray him - - That he could be in daylight .
Again , this little effect went by so fast that she drops the medicine
and he picks it up , but then it 's up high .
We were constantly doing sort of almost , like , magic
to , again , show you that she was in the presence
of someone who was not bound to adhere to the rules of nature .
I have offended you .
I am only looking for the cinematograph .
I understand it is a wonder of the civilized world .
If you seek culture , then visit a museum .
London is filled with them . Excuse me .
He 's standing there , behind her walking away .
And then as she approached , he 's standing there on the other side .
So there are hundreds of such staging tricks
to confuse her , and to hopefully delight the audience
to be in the presence of this unusual figure , you know ?
Here as a count , as also a suitor , as a lover .
Because he 's come - - In our story and in Jim Harts ' script
the innovation is that his whole reason
for wanting to once again be united with Mina
Is because of his love for Elisabeta
who , somehow , she is the reincarnation of .
I 've always had the theory myself - -
Because this theme of the reincarnation of a woman ...
And , actually , it comes up in this recent film that I 've made :
Youth Without Youth .
I 've always had the theory that , you know
a man loves the same woman all his life
even if she takes the form of different women .
But ultimately , from day one , a man loves the same woman all his life
and she is him .
You know , one of the interesting things about this Dracula story
and I think a positive thing , is that we told it as a love story .
This really wasn 't in the Bram Stoker book .
It was a little bit in the history of Vlad Tepes himself
that there was some root of this supposed story of a beloved .
And , of course , this we would credit Jim Hart for .
For finding the story , and weaving it into the Dracula story .
But I think it was the Turks deliberately sent an arrow
and we did it that way to her , saying that he had been killed in battle .
And when , in fact , it wasn 't true .
So he returned to find his beloved had killed herself .
I 'm here as your doctor .
Here , you see the extraordinary dress , wedding dress
made for Sadie Frost by Eiko Ishioka .
And this dress is an extraordinary piece of work
of design and execution , as all the costumes are .
And people can actually see these costumes
at the Francis Coppola Winery in Geyserville
in Sonoma .
It 's a beautiful , beautiful collection .
I hear mice in the attic , stomping like elephants .
I liked Sadie Frost .
She was a very nice girl , and , you know , appealing
and pretty and sexy .
I was sort of surprised .
So many young people have come through our doors
and started and go on to become great stars .
I guess she made other choices
or she had many children . She was married .
And we haven 't seen much of her after the debut in Dracula .
But she was a nice girl , and very good to work with .
I would watch my colonial tongue if I were you .
Again , I 'm always pleased
to remind the audience
that absolutely every single scene in this movie
was shot inside a sound stage .
And , you know , rarely does - - Is a movie 100 percent shot in a sound stage .
And I think this is .
And especially when we get to the bigger scenes
at the end of the big chase on the Borgo Pass .
Clearly , Lucy is being affected by her encounter with Dracula
and is being affected , in a way
affected and infected , I should say
because she has the metaphoric
blood of a vampire in her .
Which means that she , too , will be a vampire .
He 's my teacher and mentor .
Do it , man .
I guess a lot of this myth comes from , you know - -
It 's ironic , because even in modern time
we have the fear of the infected blood given to us by someone .
I mean , the whole metaphor of AIDS
and earlier diseases and plagues and leprosy .
And metaphorically , you know
a sex offender can abuse a young person
and that young person grows up to be an offender .
I guess this is a bit of knowledge that humans have known a long time
this contagion .
Astounding .
There are no limits to science .
How can you call this science ?
Here was a scene in which we tried - -
Roman and I were very pleased to do this - -
To try to portray an early nickelodeon .
And , in fact , even on the screen are some very early motion pictures
and exhibits of how magicians used illusions
and used cinema , in this - -
In the way movies were first shown in these days
in a magic room .
This shot of Dracula literally sweeping her off her feet
of course , was a mechanical effect .
He takes her , and then they 're on a little trolley that is pulled .
Stop this .
It 's interesting . When I did this shot with her
just to show the kind of kid that Winona was
she looked at me - -
I mean , she was a little too smart for her own good , in a way
as a kid . She said , " I 've already done this shot once . "
Because this was a tricky setup .
They had to step onto this moving thing .
And I said , " Oh , really ? " She said , " Oh , yes , I did it with Tim Burton . "
But I have always felt
that Winona had a deeper well of talent than she was willing to dip into .
That effect , by the way , was known as the magic box .
That was a real illusion
as was the staging of the battle at Constantinople with puppets .
And we showed the backings of how it works .
This movie is full of little treasures , that you almost have to go slow for it
and see how these things were reconstructed .
Because in this scene , with the cinema being shown
along with other novelties , the puppets , and the magic box
which was an illusion that you just saw
it was sort of like how the birth of cinema happened .
And exhibition , what became the modern movie
and , God help us , the multiplex , began as a little hall of wonders
in a way that we commemorated in this movie
you know , to show the marriage , really
of the date of the creation of Dracula , around 1900
with the birth of the cinema .
Don 't ever try this with a wolf , by the way .
This is not something you wanna do .
Again , it 's used to show
Dracula 's , you know , seduction of Mina .
The sensuality that lay under the skin of the vampire legend .
It 's so confused with sex and romance and love and death .
The two sometimes are difficult to separate , as we know
and has been pointed out in much literature
and cinema and theater .
Here we have a miniature of the manor .
It 's a small building that is meant to show at a distance away .
We played the scene at the gate .
So , yes , that 's a miniature house standing quite close to the gate
but giving the illusion of perspective .
Again , you see
there 's always an interest in modern technology in this movie .
Because it was the turn of the century , and so much was happening .
Telegraphs and telephones and microscopes and , you know
this whole dictating machines , and all kinds of stuff .
And we tried to show it all .
Now we introduce essentially a new character , Dr. Van Helsing
who 's such a important character in the second half of the story
as he is the one who comes and basically is the only force
capable of being able to resist
or hopefully have knowledge or secrets
that could counter the magical powers of Dracula .
You know , it was my - - Of course , we had a great actor .
But it was my hope or my feeling to show that anyone
who had made his profession pursuing the occult
and the strange , dark secrets of science , such as Dr. Van Helsing - -
It was my thought to try to make him a little crazy himself .
Or a little eccentric , to say the least .
You know , I encouraged the doctor to go in that direction
to be as kind of strange and colorful a character as was Dracula .
I mean , a sense - -
You had Dracula on one side of the equation
and you had Dr. Van Helsing on the other .
And they had to , in some way , be comparably weird .
Or , at least , that was the choice I made .
That blood rolling down the floor was a beautiful effect shot .
barely alive so I cannot escape .
I will try one last time today to escape to the water .
There must be passageway to the river
and then away from this cursed land
where the devil and his children still walk with earthly feet .
Again , the pixilation
to imply the vampire 's point of view .
And now we have the arrival of Dr. Van Helsing at the scene .
He is now gonna conduct the investigation
and hopefully provide the means of defeating Dracula .
I remember the window for Lucy 's bedroom - -
Talk about another homage , this big window .
I saw a movie , a great , great Frank Capra movie
which you all must see , with Barbara Stanwyck
called The Bitter Tea of General Yen . And it 's a great movie .
And there 's a big window in a bedroom somewhere
that I think was in the back of my mind
when I asked the art directors to put this window in .
A lot of Lucy 's movements here are done backwards .
And just the idea that the presence of Dracula
in the form of the shadow just would kill anything alive ...
You know , the flowers die as the shadows pass .
I always come to my friends in need when they call me .
So , Jack , tell me everything about your case .
She has all the usual physical anemic signs .
Her blood analyzes normal , and yet it is not .
She manifests continued blood loss . I cannot trace the cause .
Blood loss ? How ?
We brought in a singer
a vocalist named Diamante Galant
who provided some very orgiastic
and other feminine sounds of intensity .
And - - To help us with this sequence .
My God , she 's only a child .
Ja .
My God .
There 's no time to be lost . There must be a transfusion at once .
Interestingly , a blood transfusion
another example of modern technology at the time .
And we did it as authentically as we knew how .
We really tried to find out , well , how did they do transfusions ?
And we did it the way they did .
However , shows what a pansy director I am . I - -
It wasn 't really a transfusion , it was just a , you know , movie scene .
But the great director Clouzot , in one of his movies
actually had to have the character get a blood transfusion .
And the actors showed up , and they began to shoot the scene .
And he had brought a doctor
and they did a real blood transfusion , actually , while they were shooting it .
So I realize , you know , I 'm not as crazy as I like to think I am .
And , damn , why didn 't I have it be a real transfusion ?
But , you know , Clouzot was Clouzot , and I 'm ...
I don 't think I would 've gotten away with it .
My point that both Frankenstein and Dracula - -
Arguably America 's two favorite horror figures .
- - Come from the same root
is based on a story that actually took place on a lake in Switzerland
when four young people went on a trip .
They were Shelley , his wife , Mary Shelley
the great Lord Byron , and a friend of Byron 's , Dr. Polidori .
Now , these people in those days were sort of like
the equivalent of , you know , Snoop Doggy Dogg .
They were the hip people of the day , as when I was young
it would 've been Jack Nicholson and Michele Pfeiffer
and what have you , going off to Switzerland .
And they decided that each of them
while staying in a castle on a lake in Switzerland
would write a horror story , a ghost story , as it were .
And of course , Mary Shelley , who was not much older than 17
at that young age , wrote the classic Frankenstein .
And it 's felt that Frankenstein
was somewhat based on the intriguing character of Lord Byron .
Byron was , of course , the famous poet .
Byron was very handsome , but he had a club foot .
And so when he walked - - He was a large man .
Somehow this inspired , in Mary Shelley 's impressionable mind
the figure of the inarticulate monster Frankenstein .
And those of you who 've read the real Frankenstein book
the monster has , really , a soul
and , of course , speaks out in that desire to know why he was made
If he - - Only to suffer .
But the Dr. Polidori , who was the companion of Byron
who was probably in love with Byron
in a way that was unspeakable , he wrote a vampire tale .
And this vampire tale was Varney the Vampire
which became an enormous success in England
and ultimately inspired Bram Stoker , due to its success
to write Dracula .
And Varney was a vampire , also inspired by Byron
who was a man so charming and attractive .
And if you imagine that Dr. Polidori was secretly in love with him
the idea of a figure who , like , by his attractiveness
sucks the life , or sucks the blood out of you .
So he cast Byron in his mind as a vampire .
And so thus our two favorite characters
the monster , Frankenstein
and the vampire , Dracula , both really stem from Lord Byron .
I think this is a fascinating piece of history
behind these two classic Gothic stories .
Thinking back on this movie , it wasn 't a terribly enjoyable experience for me .
I was very happy to be there working with my son .
And I remember I was sort of in a funk during the film .
And I liked having the chance to do all these wacky ideas
and I remember being very disgruntled over the fact
that I had tried so hard , and indeed executed very hard
doing it exactly on schedule and on budget .
And so much to the point that I remember going to the executives
and saying , " Look , we 're now a week ahead of schedule
and could I have the money that that week represents
and spend it on additional special effects ? "
And they studied it and said , " Indeed , you are ahead of the budget
and so you can have the money for these extra special effects . "
And then about two weeks later , I get this visit
from this obnoxious studio executive who tells me
that they 've just gotten a bill of all people from the studio
which is to say , from them
and somehow , their accounting system was broken
but there were many , many more light rentals
and equipment rentals that anyone knew about .
And it really , you know , made me feel frustrated .
And I had tried and succeeded to make this big production
on , you know , what was not a super-affluent budget
but certainly a respectable budget .
And I had done it so carefully
and even to the point that they themselves agreed
that I was ahead of budget .
And then to be told that , oh , their billings were screwed up
and therefore , I was suddenly , magically over budget
so that they could do what they like to do so much
which is to come in and castigate you , and ...
This sequence , by the way , on a more pleasant subject
was the absinthe sequence .
And Roman did such beautiful effects work in it
10 weave the legendary and somewhat magical effects
of the drink absinthe
which was , of course , made illegal around this time
or a little later , primarily because it was the first aperitif
that was made out of something other than grapes .
And all the grape owners and makers of aperitifs
which came from grapes
really got together and got it banned for its dangerous effects .
Notably because of a murder that happened in France
where some man drank some absinthe and then got crazy
went home and murdered his family .
But no one had said that before he drank the absinthe
he had drunk two quarts of brandy
and sniffed so many tons of various other drugs .
And so absinthe was made illegal , probably quite unfairly
because it basically threatened what was the reigning business
which was making aperitifs out of grapes .
But we tried to have a love scene
with imagery liberated by the thought that they 're drinking absinthe .
As with every scene , there was a new challenge
of how can we show the past
show her resonance with the ancient woman that he had loved
and , again , present Dracula as a romantic figure
rather than just a monster ?
The princess
she 's a river ...
I think this movie
you know , was thought of many different ways .
But among the most enthusiastic people
who seem to have enjoyed the film are women .
It 's that - - I guess the nature of the love story .
I mean , everybody at some point
Is in love with someone who 's bad for them .
Certainly , being in love with Dracula would fit that description .
I thought , at the time , Winona Ryder was a very talented young lady .
And like so many people who start when they 're really young
they just have a gift .
But one of the possible problems with that
Is that they tend to not go all the way .
There comes a point where they know so much , it almost works against them .
But I will not be surprised
if Winona suddenly is in some movie at any time
and just astonishes everyone .
This is definitely an homage to Cocteau
but a lovely image .
He takes her tears and gives them to her as diamonds .
Every man would like to do that , if he makes the woman he loves cry .
Choosing a composer for a movie
Is always a very important thing in any project .
But for me in particular , being the son of a composer
being raised in a musical household
I very much wanted a classical score .
And my knowledge told me that some of the greatest classical composers
were in the East European world , particularly in Poland
partly to do with the state sponsorship of classical music .
And for a long time , the composer I really wanted to do it
was a great Polish composer named Lutoslawski .
I eventually tracked him down at a concert
where he was conducting his own work .
And when I proposed that he might consider doing a score for me
his reaction was sort of like at the level of , I mean :
" Young man , do you know how many hours it takes me
to write one minute of music ? "
And that - - The implication being that , at that level of classical music - -
And it 's not only the composition , it 's the orchestration .
- - It is a very arduous , time-consuming job
to compose so many minutes of music .
It 's not as we think of it , where , oh , you get a motif
and possibly bring in an orchestrator .
And you play the theme over and over again .
So at that level of handmade music
it 's incredibly time-consuming .
And basically , what he was saying is , you know
he wouldn 't be able to devote the time to write whatever it is
30 minutes , 40 minutes of new music .
And actually , in truth , he died not that long after that brief meeting .
But I continued researching Polish composers .
And I was very interested in Ligeti , Gorecki , many wonderful composers
some of which I heard in Stanley Kubrick 's last film .
Although it was not an original composition
I believe he used existing work of those composers .
But ultimately , I was led to consider the notion of Kilar
another Polish composer , to write this score .
And I approached him , and he was willing .
And what I noticed from that experience - -
What he wrote was very , very effective
and , in fact , really has weathered time very well .
And for years , I would see trailers of movies coming out
that had just used his music for Dracula in the trailer .
And what I noticed was he wrote about three , or at the most four cues .
I think it was three .
A love theme , a kind of initial very dramatic theme
and then a third theme .
And he gave me these three themes , and we recorded them
and that was all he gave me .
And we had a whole movie that we had to score .
And we had these three themes .
And I said , " Well , can you give me some variations ?
For example , could we play the love theme this way and that way
this orchestration , that orchestration ? "
And he tried and tried and tried
but ultimately , when it was all said and done
he wrote those three cues , they sounded great
and he was giving it to me , and that was it .
So when we actually finished the complete movie
we found that we had to take these three cues , and ...
Fortunately , we had the original recordings
which were recorded with a number of microphones .
So we could play the cue , and , you know , not play the string section
or not play the brass section
or the music editor had to find ways that we could , like
make these three very , very impressive cues
work for the whole movie without just repeating them over and over again .
And that was an interesting experience , very , very positive
and yet somewhat troublesome
with , like , a really classical musician-composer .
I guess it comes down to that , you know
every minute of music is the result of a lot of hard work .
Weeks and weeks of hard work .
And you just don 't have , you know , 12 cues
and do it this way and do it that way , and have enough for a whole movie .
You know , in a sense , it was - -
This group of young people , all the people in this scene - -
It was like being with your kids .
And for all the plus and minus of that .
You know , they were all young
and talented .
And , you know , I love to work with young people .
I always did , ever since I was a young person .
put you out of your misery like a lame horse .
Quincey .
You 're such a beast .
She 's sort of sexy with those cute little baby vampire teeth .
Will you kiss me , Quincey ?
Anthony Hopkins was , you know , a fine actor .
He didn 't like to rehearse .
And I understand it now , I didn 't then .
Because I thought all theater actors , they loved to have three , four weeks
screw around and kind of explore things .
Do it this way , do it that way .
But his disposition was such that he liked , you know - -
If there was no rehearsal , it 'd be fine with him .
Just come in and start to do it , do your job , and go home .
And so I really started off at the wrong foot with him
because I had a very lengthy rehearsal .
But I found him very cooperative .
You know , he was ultimately enthusiastic
and sort of impatient with it all .
And I don 't imagine that it was one of his favorite movies to work on .
And I think partly I took too much time in the rehearsal period
which I guess I was used to because I was a theater director
or trained in that way , and didn 't know any other way .
But now the older I get , I think , you know
maybe there 's something to speak - -
Because when you actually start to shoot , and you have the - -
You 're ready , you have the camera , the costumes , and what have you
things happen that you almost can 't rehearse
Or you can 't guess are gonna happen .
And then , you know , as I say , it 's only what you 've gathered .
It 's only , you went out picking mushrooms
and that day you got so many mushrooms .
And later on , when you cut the film
you 'll see whether or not they were useful .
You 'll make the movie out of what you have .
This scene is an example of minimalism .
The set is just basically the light and the rope .
And you get the idea she 's on a boat .
Of course , there 's nothing there but the light and the rope .
And , you know , of course I love that tradition .
And you saw much of it over the great golden age of Hollywood .
The MGM films and Warner Bros. films
where they were able to give you , by illusion , something
without having to build a whole set .
And , of course , it enables you
to spend more money on something , really , where you have to .
And you save the money in that or in this case
where it 's just some candles .
This sequence with the candles is very much the brainchild of - -
You know , the idea of having them dancing
In the candles , and what have you
was very much the brainchild of Michael Ballhaus
who was a wonderful man
and really trying to get with this , what ultimately he understood
was a kind of far-out style , in which almost anything goes .
And I think , if I 'm correct
he dreamt up the idea of a scene
where there were just some candles and what have you .
Guard her well , Mr. Morris .
Do not fail here tonight .
I remember pushing Van Helsing
in this direction that you see in this scene .
That , you know , having him really come on a little , you know ...
Well , you 're a sick old buzzard .
... hysterically , you know ?
And , you know , he 's a great actor .
And , you know , you could say :
" Oh , I encouraged him to be a little over-the-top . "
But , you know , the whole movie is over-the-top .
So , what 's over-the-top , you know ?
The top is determined by what the stylistic approach - -
And after all , we 're making Dracula here .
This is - - It 's clearly not the first time it was being done .
As I said , I think Dracula 's probably the most oft-sequelized film on earth .
And , you know , I don 't get it .
I didn 't think my job was to come in here
and do the same thing over again .
And so , you know , I took the path
that was really out of my heritage
and my background and my training
and my view of things .
And that 's all you can ask from a film , I think
Is you want a film to have a personality given to it
uniquely by its maker
that has something of the personality of the maker in it .
You know , I 'm even , these days , beginning to think
of an era in which I make movies , not only which , you know
you tend to hold closer to the vest by - -
Which is to say , you don 't show anyone the script
and you don 't ask anyone 's opinion .
But maybe even one day that you don 't even show the film to anyone .
Maybe you just make it and you look it , and then you say , " Okay . "
And then you put it in the closet drawer , and you forget it .
All you need to do that is a lot of money .
Clearly , I 've used parallel editing
and specifically in regard to a baptism in The Godfather .
Clearly , one of the tools you have in cinema is to juxtapose a ritual
a religious ritual of some type , as this is , a wedding
with other action happening at the same time .
And I 've done it before , and probably will do it again .
There 's a lot going on here , because there are these various killings
and awakening of Lucy .
So , yes , doing a collection of actions simultaneously happening
and edited parallel with a ritual
Is reminiscent of the time I did it first
which was in the baptism scene of The Godfather .
The orthodox religions , Greek Orthodox , Romanian Orthodox
Russian Orthodox , is , in fact , the original Christianity .
And for my part , I think the most beautiful expression of Christianity
that Roman Catholicism
Is Christianity having been fused with the Roman Empire
and , really , I think , has more to do with the Roman Empire
than it does with Christianity .
We 're shooting in a beautiful church here
in Los Angeles , a Greek Orthodox church .
We didn 't have this scene in the movie on the first shoot .
I forget - - I think we did it in some - - One of those stylized way
where you don 't really have anything but some shadows on the wall .
And looking at the film , I decided that having the real ceremony
the real wedding ceremony , as it might be in that religion
would be beautiful .
And this is pretty authentic , and , I think , very beautiful .
Because we actually did the ceremony , and we had the priest do the ceremony .
So in a sense , we realized when we were all done
that Keanu and Winona really are married
as a result of this scene and the ceremony .
And that 's clearly a homage
to Stanley Kubrick 's movie , The Shining .
I found the actual Romanian Orthodox churches
when I did go and spend time in Romania , which I did recently
making Youth Without Youth , very beautiful .
Maybe it 's because I wasn 't raised in it , and I 'm able to see it
as an expression of spiritual feelings
in terms of Christianity in a form that I don 't find oppressive and mean
which is how my childhood impression of religion was .
And this - - If I am talking about homage , this is Snow White in her glass coffin .
As a child , I just loved Snow White
because she had beautiful black hair , like my mother .
And I never could forget the glass coffin that she was in
and the seven dwarves mourning her .
That 's what this scene sort of looks like to me .
How can I believe ?
I want you to bring me , before nightfall , a set of post-mortem knives .
An autopsy ? Lucy ?
No , no , no , not exactly .
I just want to cut off her head and take out her heart .
Of course , when you make movies , you know
you tend to shoot in order of the set that 's up .
So that scene , the funeral scene , was shot way early in the movie
because we were shooting all the scenes in that mansion first .
And then way , way , way , later , these other scenes .
Streets of London .
For me , now that Lucy is dead , it is a sad homecoming .
It is as if a part of me is dead too
except for the tiny hope that lives in me
that I will again see my prince .
Is he here ?
Now that I am married
I begin to understand the nature of my feelings for my strange friend
who is always in my thoughts .
I don 't remember where this set was .
I know it was on some stage or another
but it 's a pretty - - I mean , this film - - Given that everything is built
with the exception of the Greek Orthodox church
which was a real church
there was a lot of work and production and sets building .
And the movie was not that costly a movie , as I recall .
I mean , nowadays , you hear of these movies that cost
you know , $ 80 million or $ 100 million .
This movie was far less than that , as I recall .
But when you look at it , you realize that everything is a set .
And all these people and costumes , and the time to do this stuff ...
I think we did it pretty economically
to put a stylish production on film for whatever it was .
I must confess , and this maybe sounds disheartening
but when I look at this and I think of , you know
all the work it is to make a movie , any movie
I have to say that unless it 's a theme
or a subject matter that you have to make
because it says something that has never been said before
or it just is in your soul , and you have to get it out
can 't see any point to wanting to make a film at all .
The way it 's been set up , and the way the whole profession has gone
it 's like you have to tolerate so much stuff .
You have to - - You work on this movie for so long
under such unenlightened directives from the company financing it .
And when it 's all said and done , they publish in the newspaper
like sports scores , how much money it did .
And they show it in a theater that 's a box with 10 other theaters .
And you have to , you know
not only hear the battery of critics
that rightly or wrongly say their opinion
but , like , absolutely everybody else .
It seems to me that the only reason to make a movie
Is because it 's something that 's never been made before
and it is really part of your feelings about life .
And therefore , it should be something
that you should finance as well as make .
Because that 's the only way that you can have the same right
that a painter has when he paints a picture
or a poet has when he writes a poem
or , to a large extent , a novelist has when he writes a novel .
Even , really , an opera composer , more or less
has the right to sit down and do his opera the way he sees it .
Of course , I suppose , to really , you know , produce Aida
you have to have someone pay for the elephants .
But you don 't hear so much about composers complaining
because the Bay of Egypt didn 't like the third act .
And what - - Of course , then , he was Giuseppe Verdi
So he didn 't have to put up with it .
A little child - - I mean , these poor kids .
I mean , the infant that I wanna meet , again , someday was just a little infant .
And we held her with great tenderness and affection .
But this little kid who was in this scene
had to be in the midst of all these obscenities
and , well , she was scared of the fake teeth and Lucy .
And can you imagine what a little 2-year-old
thinks of something like that ? It 's - -
We had a very difficult time calming her down
and getting her to even be present on the set .
Kiss me and caress me
my darling husband , please .
We wave Christ and His holy blood !
This scene
Is very much influenced by Cocteau , and ...
The candles lighting themselves .
And , of course , this scene was all acted backwards .
She was in the coffin , and started out in it , and got out .
And then we just - - We reversed it .
Winona Ryder was really thrilled with the cast .
I mean , she loved Gary Oldman
of course , Anthony Hopkins , and Richard E. Grant was one of - -
All of the actors . It was sort of her dream cast . And it was her idea .
She 's the one who gave me the script .
And in a way , I was very , very attentive to her wishes
and looked into all the actors she loved .
But she had a friend , Keanu
who was , you know , like , just a friend
and she liked very much , and thought was a very good person
and I did too .
And so we cast Keanu in the role .
But it wasn 't really my film , in a sense .
I mean , I was brought in , I was the director and what have you .
But , you know , it had been developed by other people .
You see a whole bunch of other producers and stuff on it .
And , you know , as I said , I was very fond of Keanu .
I thought he was a , you know , really nice kid .
Was she in great pain ?
Ja , she was in great pain . Then we cut off her head
and drove a stake through her heart and burned it and then she found peace .
Doctor ! Please .
So , Mr. Harker
I must now ask you , as your doctor ...
You know , from my standpoint
was doing this movie
as I said , on a string of movies that - -
I planned to do a few movies to get myself on my feet
and then I wasn 't gonna do these movies .
I wasn 't gonna do movies anymore .
I was gonna just do little personal things
which is more or less what I 've done .
- No ? - No .
Good !
Then you have not infected your blood with the terrible
disease that destroyed poor Lucy .
Doctor , you must understand .
I doubted everything
even my mind .
I was impotent with fear .
- I know . - But , sir
I know where the bastard sleeps .
I brought him there , to Carfax Abbey .
Vampires do exist .
And this one we fight , this one we face
has the strength of 20 or more people ...
I think if people really sit down
and read the Bram Stoker novel
they 'll find that this film follows the intent and the spirit of the book
closer than many .
With the one exception of the love story
which , of course , is the framing device , or the motivating device
at the beginning .
And as I say , was pretty much created by Jim Hart
in his original screenplay , which existed far before I did .
I mean , I was brought in as a director to do that script .
You 'll notice I have no screenwriting credit on this film
and that 's because , you know , beyond working as a director
making director 's suggestions
took no part in the writing of the screenplay .
planning on getting that close , doc .
You know , at the time , I thought well , I would do two movies .
I would do this film , Bram Stoker 's Dracula
and then I would do Mary Shelley 's Frankenstein
because I had a whole thought of how that should be done .
And then at the last minute , I said :
" What am I wasting my time for ?
I should be reading books or something . "
And we , of course , turned over that project to Kenneth Branagh
and , you know , was involved as a producer .
Of course , a producer , especially if the producer is a director
you have little to say to the new directors
because you don 't wanna come off as though , well
you 're some know-it-all director
who 's now gonna produce some other guy 's work .
I gave my notes to Kenneth Branagh on his version of Frankenstein
and ultimately he ...
You know , my main suggestion was they cut the first 25 minutes off of it
and get right to the story , which was the creation of the monster .
But if you see that movie , and you started a little later
a little bit more closer to the time he creates the monster
it has some interesting things in it .
That he is coming .
That he is coming for you .
Oh , please .
Don 't stay here .
Get away from these men , please .
And I pray to God I may never see your sweet face again .
And may the Lord bless and keep you .
Such a shame
that when they show these movies on television
even cable
they just cut them down .
I mean , the entire Tom Waits performance
is out of the version of Dracula that they show on television .
And it 's not because of anything other than to fit it into the time slot .
I 'm no lunatic man !
I 'm a sane man fighting for his soul !
My quarters are spare , but I think you will find them comfortable .
Dr. Jack !
Water and toiletries at your disposal .
You 'll be completely safe here .
Yeah , that set , as she walks out into the room
and then you see the remains of the abbey , that was a miniature .
Now , in the book of Dracula , the beast , as it were
was expressed in any number of forms . A wolf , a bat .
And we had a very talented special makeup-design person .
And fortunately or unfortunately , when we started shooting this movie
there was about two weeks
while Gary Oldman was waiting to do his first scenes
while we were shooting , according to the schedule , other scenes .
And Gary would hang out with Greg Cannom and just , you know
wait while he wasn 't getting to shoot .
And they would just keep coming up with :
" Oh , well , why don 't we have a creature
that looks weird like this , " and so and so .
And so , of course , every time they did
Greg would go in there at incredible cost
and create yet another weird rubber suit
that Gary would have to wear .
It 's very uncomfortable for the actors to be swathed in rubber prosthetics
and suits , and bodysuits and stuff .
And I said , " Hey , Gary , you 're the one who dreamt up this weird bat creature . "
It was - - That was the added one .
You have betrayed me .
No .
No , master .
No , I - -
I serve you .
I serve only you .
This was a live-action effect .
In other words , Roman shot the room
and then he rewound the film
and then he shot just the swirling mist going into the bed .
And it all had to - - When you develop the film and look at it
because you don 't develop the film until you make the final pass
It all has to work .
As opposed to doing it after the fact
when you can just , you know , get it exactly
So you know it is gonna work .
When you do it in the camera , you 're sort of at the mercy - -
And then if you goof it up , and you 've shot it - -
Now , of course , you shoot it a few times , so you can do a few - -
And you save one in case it doesn 't work .
But if you goof it up , and it doesn 't work
and you 've already developed it , you 're sort of dead .
what you are saying .
Yes
I do know .
I feared I would never feel your touch again .
I thought you were dead .
There is no life in this body .
But you live .
You live .
What are you ?
I must know . You must tell me .
I am
nothing .
Lifeless .
- Soulless . - What do you mean ?
Hated and feared .
I am dead to all the world .
Hear me .
I am the monster
that breathing men would kill .
I am Dracula .
No .
You murdered Lucy !
I love you .
Oh , God , forgive me , I do .
I want to be what you are
see what you see
love what you love .
Mina ...
I think if I was gonna shoot
a big , elaborate , sexy scene
involving so-called sexual activity , I would hire a fight coordinator to do it .
Because fight coordinators - -
I mean , obviously , if you 're having a knife fight
or you 're having combat and punching and stabbing and stuff
you 're not really doing it
but you have to make it look as though you 're doing it .
And it 's all done by very careful choreography .
Okay , the guy turns , and he lifts the knife
and then he brings the knife down , like , here .
And the camera sees it as being something very , very ...
You know , a hit , when in fact it 's not .
And I think the same rationale would go for shooting a sexy scene .
And if I would ever do one again , I - -
Because it 's not about , " Oh , get them in a sexy mood , and then just shoot it . "
It 's so awkward .
And the camera has to be in a place that ...
You know , when people are smooching , they 're all covering each other up .
And it doesn 't necessarily make good pictures .
So I would bring in a combat coordinator
a guy who 's experienced with staging knife fights and fist fights and things .
And say , " Okay , here 's what we gotta do .
You gotta be lying here , and you 're gonna come in here .
And it looks like you 're kissing him .
And then you reach down , and you do this and you do that . "
And it 's all done through planning
and sort of very logical and dispassionate laying out .
The same way you would do a fight . But nonetheless
I think it was Orson Welles who said the two most difficult
or convincing things to show in a movie
are people praying or people making love .
No .
I cannot let this be .
Please , I don 't care ...
I always think back
of a scene in a movie made by Stephen Frears
called The Grifters , in which the great actress Annette Bening
who was an experienced and accomplished theater actress
has to go in front of some crummy guy
and suddenly just appear there totally naked in front of him
by way of whatever the story point had to be made .
And she did that scene totally naked , not a stitch of clothing on .
And it 's so amazing
because she does the entire scene , and she never stops acting .
And that 's the objective of - - If an actress can do that
then she has conquered all the phobias that we all have .
Oh , yeah , I remember this now , also .
The fact that we had him - -
I remember I really blew my top once in rehearsal
because we were trying to stage this scene
and , you know , I 'm saying , " Okay , you 're in the wolf suit .
But , like , you 're not in the wolf suit , because we don 't have the wolf suit .
But , you know , you get up on the bed .
And , of course , they 're all frightened because you look like a bat
or whatever it is you look like . "
And he starts to get very - -
You know , he 's a very good actor , and he 's a very intelligent person .
But he started to , you know , in this early phase of rehearsal
saying to me , " Well , how can I go up on this bed
and be this weird creature
when I 'm not in the weird creature suit ? "
And I said , " Well , just pretend you are . "
And he started to get really , " How can I do it ? "
And I just lost my cool . I remember .
I kicked the chair across the room , and I just left .
And I said , " Forget it , goodbye . " And I left the rehearsal .
But , you know , I mean , I can see his part in it
that , you know , how is he really gonna go through the motions
of what it might be like if he was in a - - ?
Looked like a beast , like this .
So maybe that 's a point for not trying to rehearse .
I can remember when I was really young
was directing a movie that the young Jack Nicholson was in .
And I - - It was all in Big Sur .
And I went up there , and they were all hanging around
up in the lodge in Big Sur .
And I 'm this kind of erstwhile , young theater director from New York .
And I said , " Well , let 's rehearse . "
And Jack is saying things like , " Well - - "
You know , that was a nice effect .
The whole Dracula turns into millions of little rats .
But Jack is saying , " Well , Francis , how are you gonna rehearse ?
We 're all supposed to be out in the forest
and we 're here in this place . "
I said , " Well , we can put chairs around and say they 're trees
and we can rehearse . "
" That 's not gonna - - I don 't wanna do that . "
So I said , " Okay , we 'll rehearse out in the forest . "
And , you know , it 's funny . People who love to make movies
and love to act and love to do all this stuff
when push comes to shove - - Even composers who love to compose .
When push comes to shove , they either - -
Whether through fear or what , they don 't - -
It 's very hard to get them to do it .
You know , there 's always a million reasons of , " We can 't really do it . "
So , in this case , you know , what Gary was telling me is
that my attempt to stage this scene was sort of futile
because he wasn 't in his rat suit .
And I was saying :
" Well , we know it 's gonna be something interesting and horrendous .
So just kind of - - Let 's just work it out for the movement . "
But I guess this is what leads me to wonder
If even there 's any point to rehearsing .
I would think that the actors would welcome the opportunity
to get a chance to try out the lines
and start to feel their way toward it
and also to see what they 're getting back from the other actors
So that the characters can deepen and evolve .
But , you know , I mean , they - -
Of course , every actor is different and has their own way of doing it .
But more or less , generally speaking
as they get more and more into it , there 's a - -
Whether it 's a combination of fear , stage fright , or laziness
it 's like you really have to seduce them
to get them to finally do it .
I think one actor who was always - -
As a young person , was always really a serious - -
And just would do anything , and wanted to jump into it
and work hard , hard , hard , was Tom Cruise .
Though I , of course , never worked with him after The Outsiders .
in stormy seas
no doubt from the passage of the count 's ship .
He commands the winds , but we still have the advantage .
By train , we can reach the Romanian port at Varna in three days .
By ship , it will take him at least a week .
Now we begin the final portion of the movie
which deals with them tracking down the count
in this mad attempt to head him off
by going by train to get to Varna - -
Which , by the way , is in Bulgaria , which is now in Bulgaria .
- - Before the ship gets there .
And through a combination of these - -
Roman 's work , these miniature trains and mountains and double exposures
again , all done the old-fashioned way .
We have the race against time
as Mina is now clearly been - -
Become his bride , and is a vampire herself , no doubt .
And they are with her husband , Jonathan Harker
whom you 'll notice , his hair is becoming white
from all the horrific experiences he 's been through .
They are gonna head off Dracula
and get him before he 's able to be safe in the earth of his homeland .
No , no , I have done this to both of us .
I can hear him . He 's coming closer .
He 's calling me to him .
Mina . Mina .
Stay with me . Please .
I am so cold .
This is , you know , a glass shot
or some old-fashioned style of ' 40s studio effect .
Holmwood received a wire from his clerk at Lloyd 's .
The count 's ship sailed past us in the night fog
to the northern port of Galatz .
The black devil is reading Mina 's mind .
How can we catch him now ?
Varna . Galatz .
It 's about 200 miles .
I think that with the horses , we can cut him off
reach him before he reaches the castle .
I will dispatch Van Helsing straight for the Borgo Pass .
If we fail in our task ...
So here we had the prospect
of this huge scene in the book
where they 're racing across the Carpathian Mountains
in the snow , and train stations and stuff .
This is another effects shot . Nicely done .
where we still hoped
to intercept the count before he reaches land .
I forget , even now watching
what we had built and what we added .
I think my mind was going at this point , and I ...
You know , it was a lot of stuff to shoot in a relatively rapid time .
This is for sure a glass shot
where the road is real , and then the rest is painted .
Now here , we 're in our little - - Little ?
The huge stage
which just has , all around it , remnants of these mountains .
And this last sequence
which actually looks pretty good , is really all shot in this one stage .
Dracula has outsmarted us again .
We learned that his gypsies took charge of the vampire 's box at Galatz
and are now on the Borgo Pass road .
As I 've said before
it was great to have my son 's collaboration .
Because unlike many of the other professionals in the film industry
basically , there 's a pressure
to kind of do things the way you always do them .
And when you consider that for a second
and realize that , you know , there 's the stunt coordinators
and there 's the effects guys , and there are the prop guys
and there are all these people
and they all make one movie after another
you begin to wonder why the movies you go to see
sort of all look the same and are alike .
And it 's because the solutions to problems are done a certain way .
And when you 're making a movie and you have that stunt guy
he says , " Well , you fall off the horse this way . "
But that 's the way they fall off the horse in every movie .
And , I mean , good reason , because it 's probably the safe way .
But it 's sort of a - -
It 's an undertow when you make an industrial film
which this is
to do it the same way they 're used to doing it .
And there 's so much pressure - -
Two kinds of pressure against innovation .
I mean , there 's the fact that they don 't know how to do it another way .
But there 's also a kind of peer pressure .
In other words , if you have a photographer
and you ask the photographer to do something
stupid or unconventional
he 's worried that - - It 's not so much what you want as the director .
He 's worried what his peers are gonna say .
Is he gonna be laughed at at the photographers ' ball
when they all get together ?
So you kind of are working against a force
to have you make the film the way they 're all made .
So that nobody - - Nothing sticks out too much .
And you find that in order to break that
you have to find something excessive and demanding in yourself .
My daughter , Sophia , does it another way . She 's a tiny woman .
She 's not a - - She 's a very petite woman
and very sweet and gentle .
But she 's just hard as nails underneath .
So she 'll just say , " I don 't wanna do it that way . "
And that 's all . But when she says , " I don 't wanna do it that way "
she really is not gonna do it that way
and nothing on earth can change her .
I 'm kind of much more emotional , and ...
That was an effect , by the way
that I had tried to get the extra money for , I recall .
The women killing the horses , and all of this stuff here .
There was no money budgeted for any of this stuff .
And when I went to the company to ask permission to do these effects
recall it was related to this section .
This is the famous kukri knife
that the famous warriors from Nepal , the Gurkhas , use .
Well , so much for the three brides of Dracula .
They - - You cut off their heads , and they 're ...
They 're finished .
This is all inside . This snowy scene is all inside the stage .
And the whole subsequent chase , as I 've said before , is all shot there .
He says that the Gypsies - -
The count 's Gypsies
took control of the last - -
Of the wagon with the box of his dirt , to get him back .
And they were pursuing those Gypsies .
They 're racing against the sunset .
It may be too late . God help us .
That was to show that sort of Mina had that pixilated vision
that she wasn 't - - If she was a vampire now
she 'd need the binoculars .
That 's a classic fall-off-the-horse and-be-dragged
that some wonderful stunt guy
who 'd probably done it a hundred times , did it for us .
Harker , shoot !
It is remarkable , though
that this chase has as much variation as it has
because it 's just all shot in the same place .
I mean , it 's - - There 's hardly any set there at all .
Of course , it 's a - - This is a glass shot . It 's augmented by effects .
Those blue rings of fire , I believe , were done on an optical printer .
You can tell the difference .
I mean , the other effects , done in-camera
are much more kind of organically whole .
I mean , they 're part of the scene , because they are .
I don 't know , I think the effect has a slightly different feel .
Harker !
Much of these shots are shot by Roman
because we were , the two of us - -
We had all this slew of work to do , and all the - -
You know , every shot , every close-up , every guy on a horse and falling
and so and so , there were just so many shots we had to get .
And we were really running out of time .
And I remember we were like a two-man team here , doing these things .
And it was , as I said , pretty much in this one stage .
Mina .
I thought of that as a kind of jack-in-the-box effect
when he just bursts out of the box and it all explodes .
All that 's a live mechanical effect .
And those are tricky to do , because you really have to do them .
Or even for hitting a guy and having him fly 14 feet .
When my time comes , will you do the same to me ?
Will you ?
No .
- Wait . - No ! Let them go .
Let them go . Our work is finished here .
Hers has just begun .
Quincey .
Oh , no .
We 've all become God 's madmen .
All of us .
And for the large , large , large part
all these lines are out of the book .
Where is my God ?
He has forsaken me .
This sequence
which is the final scene between Dracula and Mina
I remember I showed - - When I was working on the film
and I showed it to my friend George Lucas .
And he looked , and he says , " Well , " he said , " you know , " he said :
" I think Mina ought to cut off his head . " "
And I said , " Wow , that 's , you know , pretty disgusting . "
And he says , " Yeah , but that 's the greatest act of - -
She could give him , is to ...
That , you know , to give him the peace
and the moment
of once again being taken to God 's breast
can only be given to him by cutting off his head . "
So I said , " Yeah , you know , there 's ... "
I hadn 't - - I mean , I hadn 't quite shot it that way .
And so I said , " Yeah , you know , I think you 're right . " And so I did .
This - - I shot her pushing the stake through the heart - -
That was the original version .
But George had thought that to really be sure
that he 's never gonna be a vampire again - -
I thought it was pretty clear .
I mean , as I did it , the sparks went in , the thing went through the heart - -
Like , the stake through the heart . But George thought , " Oh , yeah .
You should cut off his head . She should cut off his head .
That 's the greatest act of love she could do . "
And I said , " Okay , I can see it . If they don 't get it
with the stake going through the heart , we 'll cut off his head . "
It 's a pretty startling thing to do .
And I shot it late in the game , like , after the - -
You know , the film was only three weeks away from being released .
And such is the end .
And they go off to having , as lovers always do
Paolo and Francesca , Dracula and Elisabeta , and on and on .
The end .
I never - - You know , because it 's a love story
it 's kind of maybe less scary than the typical Dracula
where he 's , like , a monster .
But , you know , my idea was to make it with young people
and to make it more romantic , and , in fact , more sexy , to go , you know ...
The brides of Dracula , and the various scenes with Sadie
and then combining eroticism
when Mina begins to be infected by the blood of the vampire
that , you know , she gets to be sort of provocatively sexy .
And in fact , she was pretty sexy in that scene with Anthony Hopkins
you know , where she brings him down to her level
and almost exalts in the fact
that she has him stoked up .
So , you know , it was supposed to be a more sexy version .
I don 't feel it 's so scary a version , you know ?
Maybe a little bit
but , you know , I think the fact that it has this love story
and this love theme tends to work against that .
You know , it 's my take on Jim Hart 's script
which is , I guess , all a director can do .
I wasn 't too happy working on this film .
You know , I had made the decision at that point in my life
when I accepted what was something I thought I would never do
which was to make a third Godfather film
after really being sort of bankrupted
by my adventure on One from the Heart .
But Godfather Il led me to Dracula
and it led me to being financially solvent
which I very wisely invested
in the wine and food and resort business
and was able to achieve a final - -
Hopefully final freedom from the film industry as an industry .
And , you know , as I continue now , as I speak to you , it 's 2006
and I am just recently 67 years old .
Or as I like to call it , 50-17 .
And I decided to , you know , do what I always felt I wanna do
which is to be an amateur , and - -
Like those great Russian composers , you know , Borodin and Tchaikovsky
and people who are doctors
and professional people who just wrote music because they loved it
and they were amateurs .
I now am a businessman
in the wonderful fields of food , wine and adventure .
And if I make films , which I would like to continue doing
and am continuing to do
I 'll do it as my hobby .
I hope you 've enjoyed these thoughts and comments
stories about the film .
And I 've certainly enjoyed sharing my memories , really .
Thank you so much .